本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流
Having completed their infiltration of Ecbatana
エクバターナへの潜入を果たし
更多中日双语字幕，尽在www.kamigami.org 及微博@诸神字幕组
and gauged the likely survival of
King Andragoras and Queen Tahamenay,
アンドラゴラス王とタハミーネ王妃の生存の感触を得た
Narsus and Daryun returned
to Prince Arslan once more.
ナルサスとダリューンは　再びアルスラーン王子のもとへ戻った
いずれにしても　我々は少数すぎる
Whatever the case, there are too few of us.
How can we find more allies?
どうやって　味方を増やせばいい
To do that, Your Highness
will indicate to the people of Pars
それには　殿下が将来
今までの国政において　条理に合わぬことをなくすと
that in the future, you will
eliminate the untenable policies
that the kingdom has supported up to now.
パルスの民にお示しになるのです
One's legitimacy to the
throne is not in one's blood.
王位の正統は血にあらず
Only through righteous
statecraft can it be guaranteed.
政事の正しさによってのみ　保証されるのですから
Certainly, that is true, but if
there is a more direct stratagem...
それもそうだが　もっと直接的な策略があれば…
Forgive my saying so,
失礼ながら
but it is not for a monarch to
boast of skills in stratagem or valor.
王者たるものは　策略や武勇を誇るべきではありません
Those are the duties of his subjects.
それは臣下たるものの役目です
First, make clear what
Your Highness wishes to accomplish.
まずは殿下の目指されるものを明らかになさいませ
And it will be our pleasure
to endeavor to make that happen.
それがかなうように　我らは努力させていただきます
I will be counting on you.
よろしく頼む
These aren't my words
日听&翻译
小伍
sora
兰樱
校对
小江
mam
They're probably our words
If the whole world only had left hands
片源
Rei
时间轴
钦钦&框框
压制
久嘉
Coolkid
Don't be the bastards who hide their right hands
There's nothing beyond this azure
The day I realized that,
I stopped looking up at the sky
And in the bottomless swamp,
look, there's a bottom
In this town that's growing
even more tainted even now
Even if you just tried to breathe the air
You'd end up breathing in the bad stuff, too
And in the bottomless swamp,
look, there's a bottom
In this town that's growing
even more tainted even now
Even if you just tried to breathe the air
You are friend, Baby Dream
Before I knew it, my heart
Was full of things I had to love all the way
Always losing, leaving
Even the unbearable stuff
Because I don't want to live my days
I amenting, unable to keep them safe
You are friend, Baby, Dream
I'll grow even stronger
These aren't my words
But our words
How many in pursuit?
追っ手の数は
Five hundred cavalrymen or thereabouts?
５００騎といったところか
A tad too many.
ちと多いな
I could manage up to
four hundred on my own, but...
４００騎までなら　俺一人でもどうにかなるが
Lord Narsus, do not pay
any mind to Gieve's drivel.
ナルサス卿　ギーヴのたわ言など　相手になさらぬことじゃ
Lord Daryun will be returning soon.
もうすぐ　ダリューン殿が戻ります
Your Highness, please bear with this for a time.
殿下　しばし　ご辛抱ください
lwill.
Bravo!
お見事
The Djinn are telling me...
ジンが申しております
...that we have made the wind our ally.
我らは風を味方に付けたと
Your Highness!
殿下
Daryun!
ダリューン
This way!
こちらへ
Understood!
分かった
Over there!
あそこへ
What's that?
なんだ
This horn...
この笛は
This is bad!
まずい　退け　退け
Retreat! Retreat!
--All right!
--We did it!
よっしゃ
やったぜ
"Kashan Fortress"
A lot of slaves...
奴隷が多いな
Prince Arslan, how very
good of you to remember me.
アルスラーン殿下　よくぞ思い起こしてくださいました
I, Hodir, cannot help but be grateful.
このホディール　感謝に堪えません
Oh, no, I am the one
who must be thanking you.
いや　お礼を言わなければならないのは私の方だ
I am grateful for the
reinforcements you sent earlier.
先ほどの援軍　感謝する
I am hardly deserving of
such gratitude, Your Highness.
もったいのうございます　殿下
For my part, having learned
of our defeat at Atropatene,
私といたしましては　アトロパテネの敗北を知り
I was concerned for His Majesty
and Your Highness's safety.
国王陛下と王太子殿下のご安否を気遣っておりました
However, alone, I had no means within my power
ですが　私一人の力をもってしては
to attempt to retaliate against
the massive Lusitanian army,
ルシタニアの大軍に　復讐戦を挑む術もなく
so all I could do was worry.
ただ　心を痛めるだけでございました
However, today, Lord Daryun
presented himself at my castle
しかし　本日　ダリューン殿が我が居城に見えられ
and granted me the opportunity
to prove my loyalty to Your Highness.
私の殿下への忠誠を示す機会を与えてくださったこと
And for that, I am truly overjoyed.
誠にうれしいかぎりです
Now that you are here at Kashan Fortress,
このカシャーン城塞にいらしたからには　もうご心配はありません
you have nothing more to worry about.
First things first, please
make yourself comfortable.
まずは　ごゆるりとおくつろぎください
If there is anything you desire,
I will have it made right away.
何かお好みのものがあれば　すぐに作らせますぞ
Here at my castle, we pride ourselves
我が城の自慢は　各地から集めた食材による料理です
on dishes made of ingredients
brought in from various regions.
There seems to be an awful lot of slaves here.
奴隷が随分たくさんいるようだが
Yes, our ratio of slaves
exceeds that of Ecbatana.
ええ　奴隷の割合はエクバターナ以上です
--And we have just as great an
abundance of foodstuffs here as well.
食材の豊かさも負けてはおりません
ファランギース殿　あの男のことをどう思う
--He is a man of many words.
--What do you think?
よくしゃべる男じゃ
料理はお口にお合いましたか
--His tongue must be well oiled.
--ls our country cooking to your taste?
舌に油でも塗っているのであろう
--His tongue must be well oiled.
--Yes, it is very delicious.
ああ　とてもおいしい
--Ah! "Very delicious!"
Well, that is quite something.
おお　とてもおいしい　それはそれは
まこと　語るに落ちるとはよく言ったものだ
--Just like someone.
-Goodness! To receive praise from Your Highness
誰かのようにな
いや　殿下に褒めていただけるとは
Truly, I could not be happier.
誠にうれしいかぎりです
By the bye, Your Highness, I have a daughter.
時に殿下　私には娘がおります
She is thirteen years of age.
年は１３
Even speaking as her father,
I believe she is amply beautiful
父親の私から見ましても　十分に美しく　また利発であるように思われます
and also most sensible.
If you were to allow her
to serve you by your side,
もし　殿下のおそばに仕えさせていただけるなら
nothing would bring greater joy,
for my daughter as well.
娘にとっても　これ以上の幸福はございません
Wh-What?
Ah!
So, what steps do you intend to take
それで　憎きルシタニア兵に一矢報いるため　どうなさるおつもりですか
in order to strike back at
those hateful Lusitanians?
We must save the people of the
Royal Capital, who are suffering even now.
我々は今も苦しんでいる王都の民たちを救わなければならない
I intend to declare my
aspirations and my sincerity,
私は自らの志と誠を示し　少しでも多くの援軍を集めるつもりでいる
and gather as many as I can in reinforcements.
Ah!
And to do so, I intend to
rectify the bad, untenable policies
そのため　今までのパルスの政事で　条理に合わぬ悪政を正すつもりだ
that Pars has supported until now.
First, I plan to free the slaves.
まず　奴隷を解放しようと思う
I see.
なるほど
So, that is Your Highness's thought.
それが殿下のお考えですか　さすがですな
I would have expected no less!
Yes, would you support me in it?
ああ　賛同してもらえるだろうか
Of course!
もちろんですとも
Truly impressive, Your Highness.
Such a revolutionary idea!
さすがは殿下　革新的なお考えをお持ちだ
Well, then, this will be Your Highness's room.
では　殿下はこちらのお部屋へ　ファランギース殿はそちらへ
Mistress Farangis will have that room.
And the rest of you will be over there.
あとの方はあちらへ
Wait, I cannot leave His Highness's side.
待て
私は殿下のおそばを離れるわけにはいかぬ
We understand what you are saying,
そうおっしゃられても　このお部屋には夜具が１つしかございません
but there is only one set
of bedding in this room.
I do not care if I must rest on the ground.
床で休むこともいとわぬ
But...
ですが…
Daryun, this is not the place...
ダリューン　ここは
It cannot be helped then.
しかたあるまい
Your Highness, if there is anything,
please notify me at once.
殿下　何かありましたら　すぐお知らせください
Understood.
分かった
Your Highness, I would like to
discuss a matter of great import with you.
殿下　折り入ってお話が
What is that man plotting?
あの男は何を企んでいるのだ
It seems Lord Hodir's goal is to
make his daughter the new king's queen
ホディール卿のねらいは　娘を新王の妃とし
and to exert his influence
as the king's father-in-law.
外戚として　権勢を振るうことのようだな
So, now that we know his true motives,
と　彼の本心が分かったからには　放任しておいてよいものではあるまいな
this is surely not a matter we
can allow to take its own course.
He has purposefully separated
His Highness from us.
あえて殿下を我々と引き離した
You tell me that now?!
それを今更言うか
I was even thinking that I could 90
sleep in front of His Highness's door!
俺は殿下の部屋の前で寝てもいいと思っていたのだぞ
I played along with Hodir's hopes.
ホディールの思惑に乗ってやったのだ
Well, then, Your Highness,
では　殿下　私が申し上げたことをどうか熟考なさいますよう
please give careful thought to what I have said.
Yes, I understand.
ああ…　分かった
Considering the troop strength of this place,
ここの戦力を考えると
I would rather not make an
enemy of them right now, but...
できれば　今　敵に回したくはないが
However, if he wants to make enemies of us...
しかし　ヤツがこちらを敵に回したいと思っているなら…
Owow...
痛て…
Your Highness...
殿下
Hey...
やあ
Traversing across the balconies?!
バルコニーを渡るなど
To think you would do such a dangerous thing...
そんな危険なまねをされるとは…
There were guards, so I had no choice...
衛兵がいたので　しかたなく
What would you have done if by chance,
万が一　足を滑らせるようなことがあったら　どうされるんです
your foot should have slipped or something?!
Overprotective.
過保護
So, what did Hodir say to you?
それで　ホディールはなんと言ってきたのですか
He laid out two conditions for me.
私に２つの条件を出したのだ
One was to make his daughter my queen.
１つは　自分の娘を私の妃とすること
As for the other,
もう１つは　奴隷を解放するなどという
he counseled me against extreme
reforms, such as freeing the slaves,
パルスの伝統を打ち砕くような　過激な改革は慎むようにと進言された
which would destroy Parsian tradition.
And how did Your Highness respond?
それで　殿下はどうお答えになりましたか
I said I could not answer immediately
すぐには返答できない　明日中に返事すると言っておいた
and that I would respond sometime tomorrow.
Was that all right?
それでいいか
That should be fine.
よろしいでしょう
I swear. What is he thinking?
まったく　彼は何を考えているのか
I have not even met this daughter of his.
私はその娘とやらに会ってもいないのに
Lord Hodir is likely to
act before the night is out.
おそらく　今夜のうちに　ホディール卿は行動を起こすでしょう
Your Highness, make ready
to leave at a moment's notice.
殿下はすぐにでも出発できるご用意を
We will take care of the rest.
あとのことは私どもが片づけます
Understood.
分かった
Gieve, could I have you escort
His Highness back to his room
ギーヴは殿下を部屋に送り届けて　フランギースに伝言を頼めるか
and deliver a message to Farangis?
Consider it done.
承った
And EI am, there is something I want you to do.
それと　エラム
やってもらいたいことがある
Yes, sir.
はい
The Djinn are abuzz.
ジンがざわついておるな
The Djinn whisper to me that
I should stick my foot out the window.
ジンが窓から足を出せとささやいておる
Wait, wait, wait, Mistress Farangis.
待て　待て　待て　ファランギース殿
What do you want?
何用じゃ
A message from the Lord Tactician.
軍師殿からの伝言だ
Then you could have come through the door.
ならば　ドアから入ってくればよかろう
But there is more charm to a
lady-killer entering from a window.
窓から色男が入ってきた方が趣があるだろう
It seems your message is related
to the reason the Djinn are agitated.
どうやら　その伝言はジンが騒いでおるのと関係あるようじゃのう
Will you not swear your
loyalty to Prince Arslan for me?
アルスラーン殿下に忠誠を誓ってくれぬか
The rightful king will ascend the throne.
正当の王が即位なされる…
The rightful... king?
正当の王だと
Daryun, is something the matter?
ダリューン　どうかしたか
Narsus, I would ask for an opinion of you.
ナルサス　一つ　お主に意見を聞きたい
There is no chance that Prince Arslan
アルスラーン殿下が
is the son of the late King Osroes V, is there?
先王オスロエス五世の遺児であるということはあるまいな
That was something that
had crossed my mind as well.
それは俺も考えないではなかった
But considering when His Highness was born,
だが　殿下のご誕生時期から考えて
that is not possible.
その可能性はない
Lord Narsus, I did as you instructed.
ナルサス様　ご指示どおりにしてまいりました
Good work.
ご苦労だったな
Also, I found this in
the space above the ceiling.
それから　これが天井裏に
A cheap trick befitting the crafty Hodir.
こざかしいホディールめにふさわしい小細工だ
He likely intended to put us to sleep
我々を眠らせて　その間に　殿下を懐柔するつもりであったのだろう
and use that time to win
His Highness over to his side.
With that, we now have no need to hold back.
これで　遠慮の必要がなくなったわけだ
There appears to be a
commotion brewing outside.
何やら　外が騒がしくなってきたぜ
All right, then let us begin as well.
よし　では　こちらも始めよう
殿下
Your Highness.
アルスラーン殿下
Prince Arslan.
What is the matter?
何事だ
お休みのところ…
Forgive me for disturbing your...
What is it?
なんだ
あっ　あれは…
They are...
殿下
Your Highness.
Daryun, Narsus, and the
others by Your Highness's side
ダリューン　ナルサス　その他　殿下のおそばにあって
who will do Your Highness harm...
殿下の害となる者どもを　これから排除いたします
We will now eliminate them.
殿下のご許可を頂きたく存じます
I would like Your Highness's
permission to do so.
彼らは私によく尽くしてくれている
They serve me well.
それを排除する理由は何か
What reason is there to eliminate them?
In time, they will grow
to be treacherous subjects
彼らは　いずれ　奸臣となり
後日　殿下と祖国に害をなすことは明白です
and it is evident that they will
bring harm to you and the kingdom.
何をバカな…
What ridiculous notion is...
全ては王太子殿下の御為です
I am doing this all for Your Highness's sake!
Why do you suppose that man named Narsus
あのナルサスなる者　何故お父上のご不興を被ったと思いしめすか
incurred your lord father's displeasure?
He spoke of abolishing the system of slavery.
奴隷制度を廃止するとか　神殿の資産を没収するとか
Or of seizing the wealth belonging to temples.
貴族と自由民に同じ法を適用するとか
Or of applying the same laws to
both the nobles and the free people.
It is because he advocated such extreme ideas!
過激なことを主張したからです
それは考えあってのことであろう
I am sure he had his reasons.
Reasons?!
考え
Goodness forbid, should such a
man have his way governing Pars,
よもや　あのような者に国政を欲しいままにされたら
パルスは　ルシタニアに滅ぼされるよりも　なお悪うございます
this kingdom would be worse off
than if it were destroyed by Lusitania!
In other words, you are telling me
to forsake Narsus and Daryun.
つまり　お主は　私にナルサスやダリューンを捨てろというのだな
Indeed.
いかにも
Then, let me ask you this.
では聞くが　ダリューンやナルサスを私が捨てて　お主を選んだとして
Assuming that I forsake
Narsus and Daryun, and choose you,
how can you be sure
that there will not come a day
今度は　お主を捨てる日が来ないと　なぜ言い切れる
when I forsake you in turn?
ナルサスの悪口をお主は言い立てる
You make many unkind assertions about Narsus.
But Narsus provided me with a night of shelter
だけど　ナルサスは
私に一夜の宿を与えておいて　だまし討ちなどしなかったぞ
and never directed a sneak attack against me!
Daryun! Narsus! Gieve!
ダリューン　ナルサス　ギーヴ
ファランギース　エラム
Farangis! EI am!
We leave the castle immediately!
すぐに城をたつ
We have been awaiting your order.
ご命令をお待ちしておりました
何
What?!
Impossible!
バカな
My thanks for your aid.
世話になった
このような場所に　長居は無用と存じます
I believe there is no need for us
to remain long in such a place.
No fine women around by the looks of it, either.
いい女もいそうにないしな
Your Highness!
殿下　お待ちくだされ
Please wait!
無用な疑いを招いたのは我が身の不徳
I have only myself to blame
for inviting needless suspicion.
I will not stop you after all that has happened.
もはや　お止めはいたしません
Please at least allow my men
to lead Your Highness's horse out.
せめて　殿下のご乗馬のくつわを我が部下に取らせましょう
王太子殿下に近づくに　短剣を隠し持つとは
Approaching His Highness,
the Crown Prince, carrying concealed daggers?!
なんの謂あってのことか
What is the meaning of this?!
So, this is where it ends!
もはや　これまでか
控えよ
Halt!
It would be for your own
good to quietly let us leave.
おとなしく出ていかせた方がお主らのためだぞ
ダ…ダリューン
D-Daryun...
弓箭兵
Archers!
Wha?!
--Hey, what is this?!
--Well done.
よくやった
こ…この狡猾な狐め
Y-You wily fox!
Now, Lord of Kashan,
さて　カシャーンのご城主
we are few in number, but we have
bows and arrows, as well as bowmen.
こちらには数少ないが　弓矢もあれば射手もいる
賢明なお主のことだ
Knowing you to be the wise man that you are,
城門を開いて　我らを送り出すという考えに　ご賛同いただけると思うが
I believe we can expect you to consent
to opening the gates and seeing us out?
このままでは　私は逆賊だ
As matters stand, I am a traitor!
そうなってたまるか
And I will not endure it!
王太子を捕らえよ
Capture the Crown Prince!
くそ…
Damn it!
何
--What?!
--Where is he?!
どこだ
It's so dark, I can't see!
暗くて見えん
Damn it!
くそ
Hodir!
ホディール
問罪天使の前にまかり出て　生前の罪を告白するがいい
Present yourself before the Angel of Judgment
and confess the sins you
committed while you lived.
自分は裏切ってはならぬものを　全て裏切りましたとな
Confess how you took the
things that you must never betray
and betrayed them all!
Lord Hodir...
Your lord and master is dead!
お前たちの主君は死んだ
これ以上　死者のために戦うのか
Will you fight further for the dead?!
Your Highness, what are you doing?
殿下　何をなさるおつもりです
さあ　行くがいい
Now, go. You are all free now.
お前たちはもう自由なのだから
You have been freed from slavery.
お前たちは奴隷から解放されたのだ
Is that what Lord Hodir said?
ホディール様がそうおっしゃったのですか
ホディールは死んだ　だから…
Hodir is dead. That is why...
あんたが殺したのか
Did you kill him?
One of my companions...
私の仲間が…
What?!
なんだと
Avenge the master!
ご主人様の敵だ
私は…
やめろ
Stop this!
殿下
--Your Highness!
--Stop!
待て
先ほどの奴隷たちのことをお考えですか
Are you thinking of the slaves from earlier?
Yes.
なぜ　あの者たちはあれほど怒ったのであろうか
Why were they so enraged?
To the slaves, as bad as Hodir was,
he must have been a good master.
おそらく　ホディールは　奴隷たちにとっては
あれでも　いい主人だったのでしょう
ナルサス　お主はこうなることが分かっていたのか
Narsus, did you know that this would happen?
Yes.
はい
なぜ教えてくれなかったのだ
Why did you not tell me?
Even had I told you in advance,
先にそう申し上げても　殿下は納得なさらなかったでしょう
Your Highness is unlikely
to have been convinced.
It was my thought that
some things in the world
世の中　経験せねば分からないこともあると思いましたので
must be experienced to be understood.
それは　お主自身のことなのか
Are you speaking of yourself?
Yes.
はい
Five years ago, when I succeeded my late father,
５年前　亡くなった父の跡を継いだとき　私は奴隷を解放しました
I freed the slaves.
その後　王都に移っていたのですが
After that, I had moved to the Royal Capital,
but when I returned home after a time,
しばらくして　故郷に戻りますと
the slaves had come back.
奴隷たちが舞い戻っていたのです
Why?
なぜだ
寛大な主人の下に奴隷であることは　ある意味　最も楽な生き方なのです
In a way, being a slave under a
generous master is the easiest way to live.
だけど　お主は信念に基づいて　正義を行ったのではないのか
But did you not do what was right
in accordance with your convictions?
Perhaps what is right is not
like the sun, but more like the stars.
正義とは　太陽ではなく　星のようなものかもしれません
星は天空に限りなくありますし　互いに光を打ち消し合います
There are an infinite number
of stars in the heavens
and they cancel out each other's light.
Your Highness, whatever the case,
do not be swayed by what I tell you.
殿下　なんにしても　私の申し上げることに左右なされますな
Your Highness is attempting
to walk the path of righteousness.
殿下は大道を歩もうとしておられる
ぜひ　その道をお進みください
Please proceed down that path at all costs.
この頼もしい５人が
These five who are so
trustworthy and dependable...
いつまで　こうやって　自分についてきてくれるのだろうか
How long will they follow me like this?
I must become a worthy ruler
before they despair of me.
彼らが愛想を尽かさないうちに
自分は立派な君主にならなければならない
それで　夜が明けましたら　いずれの方角へおいでになりますか
So, come day break, which direction shall we go?
East. We head for Peshawar!
東へ
ペシャワールへ向かう
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey's beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go, drifting
When a tale that is shapeless
Spreads across the moonlight
The treasure that is within you
Melts away into the wind now
Tomorrow, try to take
wing as your unvarnished self
Sometime, somewhere,
you wanted this, remember?
You can hear it, can't you?
There; that shining dream from that day
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey's beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go
Oh, 'til this dream comes to an end
Lord Vahriz.
ヴァフリーズ殿…
なぜ　こんなとんでもなく重い置き土産を
Why did you leave this
terribly weighty parting gift
わしのような無能者に残していかれたのじゃ
to a man of few talents such as I?
The Royal House can trace its history
back to the Hero King Kaykhusraw,
英雄王カイ・ホスロー以来続いたパルス王家も
but if matters should go wrong,
it could very well end here.
まかり間違えば　ここで終わってしまうかもしれぬ
I would have been better off
had I died two kings back
先々王ゴタルゼス様の盛んな御世に死んでおいた方が　ましだったわい
during King Gotarzes's prosperous reign.
ギーヴはぼやいた
Gieve grumbled.
６人が３組に分かれるなら
If the six of them were to split three ways,
彼はむしろ　ファランギースと行動を共にするつもりだった
he was more inclined to accompany Farangis.
次回　ペシャワールへの道
Next time, "The Road to Peshawar."
"Chapter XI
The Road to Peshawar"
少年は　そして王となる
And thus, the boy would become king.